<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: protest | This Is A Test]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.schwern.net/categories/protest/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.schwern.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-17T17:46:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.schwern.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael G. Schwern]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[YAPC::NA 2012 - This Has All Happened Before And Will Happen Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.schwern.net/2013/05/16/yapcna-2012-poor-director-behavior/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-16T13:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.schwern.net/2013/05/16/yapcna-2012-poor-director-behavior</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YAPC::NA Series</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal/">YAPC::NA 2013 Will Not Enforce Its Code Of Conduct</a></li>
<li>YAPC::NA 2012 &ndash; This Has All Happened Before And Will Happen Again</li>
</ul>


<p>A lot of people, when they see <a href="/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal/">a public post like mine about harassment</a>, they assume it&rsquo;s the first and only incident.</p>

<p>Going public is seen as, let&rsquo;s see what I&rsquo;ve gotten so far&hellip; &ldquo;hypersensitivity&rdquo;, &ldquo;sensationalism&rdquo;, &ldquo;tempest in a teapot&rdquo;, &ldquo;a manifesto&rdquo;.  What they don&rsquo;t realize is it&rsquo;s usually a latest (but unlikely last) in a long chain of small and large incidents.  The reporter usually tried to get involved via normal channels, and were rejected.  They tried to alert others and to affect reform, and were probably told it wasn&rsquo;t a problem or that they should do more themselves.  After that they probably withdrew quietly.  By this point all community systems have failed me.  Taking an incident to the court of public opinion is the <em>last</em>, <em>most dangerous</em> and <em>most exhausting</em> option.  I risk not only the ire of the community, but of the whole internet, with the added issues which come with making a complaint public.</p>

<p>If you think I&rsquo;m over reacting, or that I should just calm down, then let me tell about the time YAPC::NA 2012 harassed their keynote speaker for trying to discuss the Code Of Conduct.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In early 2012 I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TAOxGjNbp_Y">invited to keynote YAPC::NA 2012</a> by its director<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.  This was an honor for me, a <em>huge</em> honor!  Keynoting YAPC::NA was a huge deal for me, this is the conference where I got my start speaking.  This is <em>THE</em> Perl Conference for North America!</p>

<p>By this point I had heard a lot of my friends privately stating they don&rsquo;t go to OSS conferences any more because they have been, or are fearful of, being abused.  I didn&rsquo;t know how YAPC::NA was dealing with this, so I had a look.  <a href="http://www.yapc2011.us/yn2011/conduct.html">YAPC::NA 2011 had a pretty good Code Of Conduct</a>, but YAPC::NA is run by a different group every year.  If you look at <a href="http://2012.yapcna.org/conference/code-of-conduct">2012&rsquo;s CoC <em>now</em></a> it looks pretty good.  It wasn&rsquo;t always that way.  And like this year, it had no teeth.</p>

<p>This is <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20120121074332/http://www.yapcna.org/conference/code-of-conduct">the originally published YAPC::NA 2012 Code Of Conduct</a>.</p>

<pre><code>Code of Conduct

At YAPC we do not tolerate harassment or illegal activities of any
kind. We respect each other's differences, tastes, and
beliefs. Because of this mutual respect, our code of conduct is
quite simple:

1. We expect all conference attendees to treat each other with respect.
2. If a crime has been committed, call the Police.
3. If someone is harassing you, ask them politely to stop.
4. If they don't stop, report them to one of the YAPC staff; they are
   wearing black "YAPC Staff" shirts.
</code></pre>

<p>This is a weak and problematic Code for many reasons<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.  Here&rsquo;s a fundamental one: we don&rsquo;t agree on what &ldquo;respect&rdquo; or &ldquo;harassment&rdquo; mean.  We <em>think</em> we do, but we really, really don&rsquo;t.  We think Perl folks share a whole heap of values, but especially at conferences where 50% of the attendees are new, we&rsquo;re just a bunch of people who use the same programming language.  The Director goes on to demonstrate this in spades.</p>

<p><a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo1.txt">I told the Director so in polite detail</a> and suggested a few already written and vetted ones they could adopt. If I made a mistake, it was in being more than a bit long winded and perhaps a bit preachy.  The CoC was so simplistic and committed so many basic errors that I made assumptions about my audience and I had my hackles up..  Knowing it would be a touchy subject, I offered to speak over the phone, since <a href="http://opensourcebridge.org/sessions/783">email can be problematic for tense conversations</a>.  However, this was nothing to earn <a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo2.txt">the response I got</a>.  Here&rsquo;s some excerpts&hellip;</p>

<pre><code>I simply refuse to list bullet point examples of infractions. I'll
be the judge of infractions...

The extra words on the web site aren't going to change people
from being assholes into polite society, nor will they make anyone
feel more safe...

I've talked to a dozen people that feel exactly like you do and
they've all tried to convince me of exactly what you're saying...

A policy would not have prevented that sort of thing [the
ApacheCon incident] from happening, and if you believe it would,
you're delusional...

I will not put bullshit words on a web site and act as if they'd
have any affect real world situations...
</code></pre>

<p>That could have gone better.  The Director is giving the classic <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Why_anti-harassment_policies_should_be_public">&ldquo;we shouldn&rsquo;t list what harassment is&rdquo; argument</a>, and more than a bit aggressively.  He&rsquo;s expressed that he doesn&rsquo;t really believe in the Code Of Conduct, that words won&rsquo;t change anyone&rsquo;s behavior.  What he does believe in is a purely punitive system with justice solely doled out by him.  It&rsquo;s clear that he&rsquo;s very passionate about protecting people, but it&rsquo;s also clear the only point of view he&rsquo;s considering is his own and perhaps his friends.</p>

<p>At this point the conversation hasn&rsquo;t gone completely off the rails.  It&rsquo;s rapidly heating, but not personal.  <a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo3.txt">I tried again</a>.  I fully admit talking about &ldquo;white guys&rdquo; wasn&rsquo;t a good choice, but it doesn&rsquo;t measure up to what I got back.  These are the sort of things <a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo4.txt">I got in reply</a>&hellip;</p>

<pre><code>I have listened to the experts, and you're not it. Neither are the
dozen people who have been harassing me about it. The only people
who give a shit about this are white guys like you...

How many people do you know that have been raped? I know seven...

I know the people that are marginalized by society, because they
are around me all the time. I think I have a better vantage point
than you to make a judgement about what is or is not a good code
of conduct...
</code></pre>

<p>Keep in mind, this is the Director of a Perl conference replying to a concern of his invited keynote speaker whom he has never met.  <em>We had never met</em>, there is no pre-existing anything between us personally.  This suddenly got really personal, really ugly, really fast.</p>

<p>While I was still recovering from that, <a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo5.txt">another one came in</a> which I&rsquo;ll produce here in it&rsquo;s entirety.</p>

<pre><code>Before you come back to me with yet another response about what a
terrible person I am, or that I don't understand because I'm a
white guy, I want to head you off at the pass.

I think its great that you're out to make the world a better
place, but save your effort for areas that need it.

If you don't want to come to YAPC because I won't take your advice
about the Code of Conduct, that's fine.  Several other white guys
that sit on high horses have told me the same thing. If you think
I'm not doing a good job of running YAPC, then put in a bid for
yourself next year, and you can write whatever code of conduct you
would like. Or feel free to use your keynote time at this YAPC to
tell the audience how terrible this YAPC is going to be because
it's missing a few words from the web site.

The point is, you're not going to convince me to change my
mind. Just let me know if you want to back out of they keynote, so
I can assign it to someone who wants it.
</code></pre>

<p>Let&rsquo;s break that down.</p>

<ul>
<li>He&rsquo;s taken my comments about the CoC extremely personally.</li>
<li>He&rsquo;s convinced I&rsquo;m going to use the keynote to bad mouth the conference.</li>
<li>I have been told if I don&rsquo;t like how the conference is run I should just not come.</li>
<li>In discussing harassment I have gotten harassed.

<ul>
<li>By the head of the conference.</li>
<li>By the person in charge of anti-harassment.</li>
<li>By the sole arbiter of what is and is not harassment.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Many people pointing out a problem is not seen as a reason to review the problem.</li>
<li>He will not change his mind.</li>
<li>If you appear to question his authority, you will get shit for it.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is not acceptable behavior for a conference director, to say the least.</p>

<p>At this point it was quite obvious the Director has issues about the CoC that have nothing to do with me.  I stepped in some existing shit.  There&rsquo;s clearly an insecurity about his authority.  He&rsquo;s feeling pressure from a lot of avenues and has thrown a tantrum.  While it&rsquo;s a shame he&rsquo;s under pressure, this is his job.  Pressure is not an excuse to lash out.</p>

<p>This was three months until the conference and already he&rsquo;s broken down under the pressure of having his CoC questioned.  What happens <em>during the conference</em> when he&rsquo;s really under pressure?  What happens when someone comes to him, the sole arbiter of what is and is not harassment, with a serious problem?  What if he&rsquo;s in a bad mood and decides their problem is not a problem?  At best, they&rsquo;re left unprotected.  At worst, he lashes out at them and they get more harassment.</p>

<p>The conversation was nasty, going nowhere, and clearly not about me.  I stopped replying, but I couldn&rsquo;t leave it at that.  This was NOT the person who should be deciding what is and is not harassment.  This was NOT the person vulnerable people should be going to for help.  I asked around and learned others tried to have this conversation with him and <a href="http://blog.urth.org/2011/09/05/conference-code-of-conduct-considered-crucial/#comment-389">got a similar response</a>.</p>

<p>If he&rsquo;s not going to listen to men, maybe he&rsquo;d listen to women.  I informed a few friends who are women and were planning on attending about the CoC and the Director&rsquo;s attitude and let them have at it.  For my efforts, I received this email from him.</p>

<pre><code>From: ********* &lt;admin@yapcna.org&gt;
Subject: you're an ass
Date: Wed, 14 Mar 2012 00:13:20 -0500
Message-Id: &lt;E40F5314-8F19-4A29-B0D5-E8B0D5FCDBF0@yapcna.org&gt;
To: Michael G Schwern &lt;schwern@pobox.com&gt;

You couldn't convince me so you decide to sick your friends on me.
That's not going to help your case or your cause. Stop.

********
Director, YAPC::NA 2012
http://www.yapcna.org
</code></pre>

<p>One of the biggest reasons people don&rsquo;t report harassment is because you tend to get more harassment.  <em>Especially</em> if the harasser finds out you reported them.  Here is the self appointed arbiter of harassment, coming after me because I spoke about his bad behavior to others.  Because I reported his harassing behavior, I get attacked.  He has violated one of the fundamental principles of handling an incident: you protect the people involved.</p>

<p>Having no higher authority at YAPC::NA 2012 to appeal to, I sent the emails to <a href="http://www.perlfoundation.org/">The Perl Foundation</a> in the hopes they could do something.  I was informed, regretfully, that once YAPC::NA has been handed off to a group TPF has no authority to intervene.  However, they were looking into changing that&hellip;</p>

<pre><code>Because of that we have been looking at this issue and put together a
small group of people who are working to create a Code of Conduct and
a set of procedures to be followed at a conference.  The idea being
that when we make a call for future conference organisers that we make
it clear that we are expecting and promote a particular set of
guidelines.
</code></pre>

<p><a href="http://blog.schwern.net/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal/">That didn&rsquo;t work out so well</a>.</p>

<p>I spent days deciding whether or not I should attend or withdraw.  Was the keynote worth it?  Or would it be more worthwhile to publicly withdraw and find out who else had abuse heaped on them by this guy?  I am his keynote speaker and a prominent member of the Perl community with all the power and privilege you can get.  He treated me extremely poorly.  What is going to happen to a mere attendee?</p>

<p>In the end, other people got through to him.  The CoC was replaced by the very good <a href="http://opensourcebridge.org/about/code-of-conduct/">Open Source Bridge Code Of Conduct</a> (one I suggested in the first place).  The Director apologized to me for his hostility.  I never made this incident public.  Strange thing is, re-reading his emails now I see he believed passionately about protecting people, but his approach was egotistic, disrespectful and hostile in the extreme.</p>

<p>I have been to a lot of conferences, and I have engaged them about all sorts of issues.  This is the worst and most shocking treatment I have ever had by a conference organizer. If it were not for the importance of the keynote topic I would have withdrawn and advised others did so too.  I had no faith that the CoC would be upheld and certainly would not send vulnerable people to such a person as the Director for help.  The poor treatment by the Director, in concert with the extreme touchiness of my choice of keynote topic, made for a very unpleasant few months leading up to the conference.  When I said at the end of the keynote I would take no questions it was because I was an exhausted wreck.</p>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s time for YAPC::NA 2013.  I&rsquo;ve had a nasty fight over the CoC in 2012.  I&rsquo;ve already been harassed by a YAPC::NA conference organizer once.  I did not have much patience to be told by the 2013 organizer that building CoC procedures and enforcers was not necessary.  The alarm I raised in 2012 has largely been ignored.  While there was talk, the procedures promised by The Perl Foundation do not exist or failed.  I tried to go through normal channels last year and got nowhere.  <a href="/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal/">I tried to go through normal channels this year and got nowhere</a>.</p>

<p>This is not the first time conferences have botched the Code Of Conduct, and it won&rsquo;t be the last.  Making this public is not my option of first resort, it is my option of exhausted <em>last</em> resort in the hopes that making the information more widely available to the actual and potential users of Perl will cause change.  Verbal abuse or physical abuse, whatever the reason&hellip; nobody should have to go through it to speak at or attend a Perl conference.  <em>Period</em>.  Now I&rsquo;ve gone through it once, I won&rsquo;t stand going through it twice.</p>

<p>You may have noticed I&rsquo;ve omitted the Director&rsquo;s name from this story as much as possible.  In part because he apologized last year, and he behaved ok this year.  But more because I really don&rsquo;t want to bad mouth him or YAPC::NA.  I fretted about whether I should dig this up and post it in public, and I&rsquo;m a privileged white guy with power in my community and little risk of real backlash.  A lot of other people don&rsquo;t have that privilege.  And yet my impulse is <em>still</em> to protect YAPC, protect Perl, protect the people involved and give them all the chances to correct the problem.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m making this public because I have raised the alarm many times before and it has been ignored.  People inside YAPC::NA, TPF and perl.org still think behavioral oversight is <em>optional</em> and while they might fret about it they won&rsquo;t take action.  When someone tries to, they get shit for it.  When an incident does occur, there&rsquo;s no process in place to deal with it.  Over and over again.</p>

<p>I am not the first by far in Perl to raise the alarm.</p>

<p>Dave Rolsky made <a href="http://blog.urth.org/2011/09/05/conference-code-of-conduct-considered-crucial/">a fantastic post on the subject</a> in September 2011, deciding to go ahead and give YAPC::NA nine months to get their act together.  The 2012 Director clearly saw it <a href="http://blog.urth.org/2011/09/05/conference-code-of-conduct-considered-crucial/#comment-389">and made comments</a>.  Dave makes some <em>excellent</em> points in that post, particularly on the subtle details about what a Code Of Conduct really means, and moderates the comments like a boss.</p>

<p>Before that in July 2011 there was <a href="http://radar.oreilly.com/2011/07/sexual-harassment-at-technical.html">a very public stink about OSCON&rsquo;s lack of a Code Of Conduct</a> which I participated in and discussed with many Perl folks.  It was pretty much all I did at OSCON 2011.  While at had its bumps, it was handled fairly gracefully and things turned out better in the end.</p>

<p>Before that at OSCON 2009 Skud gave her keynote <a href="http://infotrope.net/2009/07/25/standing-out-in-the-crowd-my-oscon-keynote/">&ldquo;Standing Out In The Crowd&rdquo;</a>.  My 2012 keynote cribs heavily from her message.  She received a lot of abuse for that keynote.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s just the public Perl ones I can think of.  I&rsquo;m sure there are more.  Have a read through the <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Timeline_of_incidents">Timeline Of Incidents</a> and consider.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Note that YAPC::NA is run by a different group every year.  The 2012 and 2013 directors are different people.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>More on that in great detail <a href="/static/yapc2012-coc-convo1.txt">my initial post to the Director about this</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[YAPC::NA 2013 Will Not Enforce Its Code Of Conduct]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.schwern.net/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T20:18:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.schwern.net/2013/05/15/yapcna-2013-withdrawal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YAPC::NA Series</h2>

<ul>
<li>YAPC::NA 2013 Will Not Enforce Its Code Of Conduct</li>
<li><a href="/2013/05/16/yapcna-2012-poor-director-behavior/">YAPC::NA 2012 &ndash; This Has All Happened Before And Will Happen Again</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not going to <a href="http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/">YAPC::NA</a> this year.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d been involved with the planning process for months, speaking with
the Todd Rinaldo (the conference organizer) and volunteers.  I have stopped.  I&rsquo;d been <a href="http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/talk/4664">accepted for a talk</a>.  I have withdrawn it.
I&rsquo;d originally been offered to do a short keynote about the deeper
meaning of the Code Of Conduct, a follow up on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TAOxGjNbp_Y">my keynote last year</a>.  That&rsquo;s not
happening.  I introduced three people to help out the conference: a
project manager, an event coordinator and an experienced Open Source
conference organizer.  Two were accepted speakers.  They have all
withdrawn. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/schwern_Ineffective_Perl_Programming.jpg" title="Schwern at YAPC::NA 1999 giving Ineffective Perl Programming" ></p>

<p>For those who don&rsquo;t know me or YAPC::NA, I&rsquo;d like you to understand
how serious not going is for me, and how things have
become toxic enough for me to speak out publicly about YAPC::NA and
perl.org.  I&rsquo;ve been doing Perl since about 1995.  When you install a
Perl module, it probably goes through at least
<a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::Harness">three</a>
<a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::More">different</a>
<a href="https://metacpan.org/module/ExtUtils::MakeMaker">subsystems</a> I&rsquo;ve
written, maintained or overhauled.  I got my start speaking at the
first YAPC::NA in 1999 and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TAOxGjNbp_Y">keynoted in 2012</a>.  YAPC::NA has gone from being a cheapie, self-organized
Perl conference to, effectively, The Perl Conference in North America.
To not go to YAPC::NA means you miss the biggest Perl event of the
year, a chance to see friends, and the biggest opportunity to speak and be heard. <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot which has gone wrong with YAPC::NA, and a lot to talk
about.  Some of it is very personal.  It&rsquo;s going to take a whole
series of posts.  What I&rsquo;m going to start with is the biggest,
clearest problem.  They have stated the <a href="http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/code-of-conduct.html">Code Of Conduct</a> will not be
enforced on their own IRC channel during the planning process.  I doubt it can be trusted
during the conference.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to get into the incidents, the details are not important
for this story right now.  How they were handled is the real problem.
There were incidents and the CoC process failed.  The particular
incident in question was verbal abuse against a volunteer on <a href="http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/wiki?node=WebchatIRC">#yapc, the advertised conference chat channel</a> by several
people including channel operators and a irc.perl.org server
administrator.  I was informed of the abuse by the volunteer and asked
to intervene.  It escalated from me speaking with the server admin, to
the YAPC::NA Director, to <a href="/static/yapc2013-coc-complaint1.txt">an official Code Of Conduct complaint</a> including logs of the
conversations.</p>

<p>The YAPC::NA Director&rsquo;s replied saying he&rsquo;d forward it onto the proper
CoC channel, but it concluded with&hellip;</p>

<pre><code>Thank you for letting me know, but this is an IRC issue. I've
given you my opinion. But that's all it is. Is it your expectation
that COC should have a year round operation? I'm not aware of
anything that indicates this I definitely do not have an interest
in performing these duties.
</code></pre>

<p>I received a <a href="/static/yapc2013-coccom-reply1.txt">reply to my complaint</a> from
the president of <a href="http://www.perlfoundation.org/">The Perl Foundation</a> speaking for the
Code Of Conduct Commitee.  It contains this.</p>

<pre><code>The scope of the Code of Conduct, however, does not extend to
conversations on the #yapc channel that take place a month before the
conference begins.
</code></pre>

<p>This is <em>the only</em> communication I have seen from this body.  I&rsquo;ve
never heard of them before.  They have been conspicuously absent from
CoC discussion in YAPC::NA planning.  Their only action is to say they
will take no action.  If they will not take action, what is the point
of this commitee?</p>

<p>From the highest authorities I am told the Code of Conduct does not
apply to the times before the conference nor to their advertised IRC
channel.  This is highly distressing.</p>

<p>It leaves volunteers unprotected during the planning process on an
advertised conference IRC channel.  Despite a clear request for
intervention, with all the information already gathered and presented
for them, no action will be taken.  The incident was not even
discussed.  As far as I know, nobody contacted the people involved in
the incidents in an official capacity.  They didn&rsquo;t even express to
the abused volunteer they&rsquo;re sorry they were given a hard time.</p>

<p>A YAPC::NA volunteer was verbally abused by a long time server admin
with power and authority in the community.  I tried to discuss it with
him and was met with more abuse.  I followed the expected channels for
escalating a report, and was met not just with inaction, but outright
refusal to take action and the information that we are unprotected.  I
followed procedure and it went nowhere.  The major concern was not
that there was harassment, but with how much effort it might take to
police things.</p>

<p>This is deeply, deeply wrong.</p>

<p>Protecting your volunteers should be a <em>no brainer</em>.  The CoC
committee&rsquo;s priority should be to listen to and protect people with
any association with the conference, at any associated event, venue or
communication medium and at any time associated with the conference
planning, events or aftermath.  Period.</p>

<p>Some of these volunteers, and at least half the attendees, are new to
the Perl community.  They have no connections, no power and no
authority.  If the conference organizer and the CoC committee will not
defend them, will not step in on their behalf, who will?</p>

<p>I have left the conference because this, and other conversations with
the YAPC::NA organizers, demonstrates that the CoC isn&rsquo;t worth the web
page it&rsquo;s written on.  The CoC process has already broken down and the
conference hasn&rsquo;t even started.  The CoC Committee and conference
organizer have stated they are not invested in protecting people.  The
CoC is being treated as some optional chore.  Some contractual
obligation where YAPC::NA is only going to meet the minimum
requirements.</p>

<p>Fortunately, this was a relatively minor incident.  Nobody was
physically abused and the verbal abuse was <em>relatively</em> minor.  What
if this were a major incident?  What if someone were told &ldquo;sorry, we
don&rsquo;t have the time&rdquo; or &ldquo;we don&rsquo;t think your problem is a problem&rdquo; or
&ldquo;they had every right to act like they did, they were busy&rdquo; or &ldquo;that
happened before/after the event&rdquo; or &ldquo;even though we sent you there,
you were in a place we don&rsquo;t enforce or control&rdquo;?</p>

<p>You might think &ldquo;well, if this were a <em>real</em> incident they&rsquo;d take care
of it&rdquo; and that&rsquo;s all wrong.  The point of a CoC is you <em>don&rsquo;t</em> get to
decide what is and is not a problem for someone else.  There was an
incident reported, someone had a problem at your event, you deal with
it.  Before you rule on the matter.  Before you decide if it&rsquo;s a CoC
violation.  Somebody was hurt enough to report a problem.  No matter
how <em>minor</em> or <em>silly</em> you might think it is, you uphold the CoC.  You
help the people at your event.  This does not mean you start handing
out punishment, or that you even have to start assigning blame.  The
CoC is there because we&rsquo;re all different, we have different needs,
different values, different problems, and we <em>don&rsquo;t</em> agree on them.
You at least acknowledge that their problem is a problem <em>for them</em>.
You at least speak with the people involved.  You mediate.  You
intervene.  <em>You get involved with people</em>.</p>

<p>The YAPC::NA organizers, and the CoC commitee, clearly are not getting involved.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not enough to just have a list of rules, you must get people
involved.  Why?  Because people are <em>messy</em>.  People are
<em>complicated</em>.  Their problems are complicated and messy.  They&rsquo;re the
sort of problems we can&rsquo;t <em>just</em> write rules for, can&rsquo;t write a
program for.  People have to be involved to interpret those rules, not
according to their letter, but according to their intent.  The CoC is
not just a list of rules, it is the foundation of a system of justice.</p>

<p>Why?  Because nobody else can be counted on to do it for an outsider.
Because people should be able to volunteer for and attend a Perl
conference without having to fight.  Most of all because people are
coming to Perl and getting treated badly right now.</p>

<p>That is the job of a <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment/Duty_officer">CoC enforcer</a>.
This person&rsquo;s job is to receive complaints and respond to people in
crisis without being too busy or worrying about other conference
issues.  They are there for the people.  YAPC::NA does not have CoC
enforcers, nor <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment/Policy_resources">enforcement policies</a>.
I tried to warn the organizer months ago, and members of TPF last
year, that it was not enough to just have a CoC.  That it was not
enough to leave it to one person, there need to be people on the
ground and comitted to helping people.  I pointed them at existing
resources, the
<a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment/Policy">Geek</a>
<a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment/Policy_resources">Feminism</a>
<a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment/Duty_officer">resources</a>
for one.  I suggested they adopt the <a href="https://github.com/python/pycon-code-of-conduct/blob/master/Attendee%20Procedure%20for%20incident%20handling.md">PyCon Attendee</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/python/pycon-code-of-conduct/blob/master/Staff%20Procedure%20for%20incident%20handling.md">Staff Procedures</a>.
There was was some enthusiasm around this, but nothing official came
of it.  The YAPC::NA director thought the CoC was enough.  He refused
to do the work.  The CoC commitee has refused.  The whole thing
breaks.</p>

<p>YAPC::NA cannot be counted on to enforce their CoC.</p>

<p>There is a dichotomy in perl.org.  There are people who are primarily
concerned with the CoC as a restriction on their behavior, because
they&rsquo;re afraid it might be used against them, or that they&rsquo;ll have to
take time to enforce it, or that it might make them uncomfortable.
There are others who see it as protection, as a fundamental
requirement for any community they are involved in, because they might
have to use it.  YAPC::NA and perl.org are dominated by people who
look at this as a restriction, for them it is an optional hassle.</p>

<p>The CoC is for people who <em>do not</em> have the protection of the
community.  Who do not know or go against the community norms.  People
who are at risk against backlash for speaking out.  People who do not
hold power and do not know people who do.  People who cannot or do not
want to fight.  The CoC process is their advocate.  The CoC is for
them, first and foremost, so they can participate and enjoy YAPC::NA
and Perl the same as the people with power and privilege do.  The
conversation within YAPC::NA is skewed in the wrong direction.  It is
skewed towards the restrictions and hassles of the privileged, away
from protecting people.</p>

<p>People are being abused.  People are leaving the conference.  People
are leaving the community. The conference has lost three speakers, a
project manager, an event coordinator, and an experienced OSS
conference organizer.  One is new to Perl and programming and wanted
to find out more.  One is a former YAPC::NA speaker and prominent OSS
member.  One is a former Perl Mongers leader.  One, myself, has the
highest level of power and experience in the community as you can get.
We cover the spread of power and experience with Perl.  We have all
left in disgust or fear over the CoC process.  And these are just the
people I know about.</p>

<p>People like to think it doesn&rsquo;t happen, that Perl is somehow
exceptional.  But this sort of mistreatment happens, even here.  This
isn&rsquo;t the first time, and I&rsquo;m not the first to speak out.  But it <em>is</em>
the first time I&rsquo;m being loud about it.  Let&rsquo;s start being loud.</p>

<p>If you would like to express your opinion to the conference, email the <a href="mailto:admin@yapcna.org">YAPC::NA 2013 director at admin@yapcna.org</a> and the <a href="mailto:coc@yapcna.org">Code Of Conduct Commitee at coc@yapcna.org</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I am still doing my <a href="http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/training.html#git1">&ldquo;Git For Ages 4 And Up&rdquo; classes</a>. It wouldn&rsquo;t be fair to the students who signed up, booked extra hotel nights and took time off to attend if I cancelled.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>YAPC::NA is not directly associated with <a href="http://www.yapceurope.org/">YAPC::Europe</a> or <a href="http://yapcasia.org/">YAPC::Asia</a>.  They are organized by different groups.  I don&rsquo;t have details about how they&rsquo;re run.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
